so now what I want to do is try to give
you a little idea of some of the ways
that we have organized this first summer
soul experience in order to address some
of that larger vision now have this
little diagram I made this morning which
I hope you can see
so we've designed the experience the
learning experience at all the law
around three primary modes of
educational experience and I see this as
a generative process that that this
process enables improvement in this
process which enables improvement in
this process and really generates a
whole learning experience so one part
one stream of the experience is has to
do with research the ability to come up
with novel questions about that are not
that are not gnomes and to start a
process of active inquiry and research
in a way that moves that question along
and the way that we support the research
of the student is through insight
practice because you can't ask questions
of the unknown without having at least
some insight some insight as to a
hypothesis or a proposition or a
relevant question and that what that
looks like my marrow
is collective insight we do collective
insight practice here at at all the Lord
all the lawyers the home of all dolor
insight center students engage in what I
call contemplative science because it's
a science to do research but the
contemplative aspect of it is the
ability to watch into compo contemplate
and be self-reflective of one's in sight
process and why does it matter so this
generates novel questions and novel
approaches to a research project so we
have contemplative science collected
inside practice and the research
the other process stream is a project
stream so in order to do the research it
needs to be designed into a project so a
project could be a multimedia project it
could be an interview project it could
be a research traditional academic
research project working through the
internet it could be a building project
an actual physical project to answer
some questions and experimental set set
up so we have a project stream now the
project stream one of the skills that
you need to cultivate to support a
project stream is embodied leadership
because with a project you have to start
to access and gather resources and
you're not going to do that by just
having contemplative insight you need
some embodied leadership you need to go
out in the world and interview people
you need to go out into the world and
get resources for your experiment or
your built project and that projects in
evitable create a living center or a
community of practice so that this
process dream is the project embodied
leadership in the community the
community that you're leading in an
embodied way in order to achieve your
project so those are quite academic and
scientific and challenging in
an intellectual way but the third
process dream I think has gotten
increasingly important and it's
something that's left tradition left out
of almost all educational design and
that is practice or practical or a
practicum so you can't just do a project
all of a sudden you're going to do it
once it just shows up now that's true in
institutional situations where the
institution will throw resources and
support and really do all the leadership
you can give the student the the sense
or at least the false sense that the
project is being led by them but the
real way that research projects and
action gets done in the world we know
requires a lot of practice and when
students are robbed of the challenge of
practice they are robbed of the
opportunity to develop the skill set
that they need to face an unknown future
so practice life underneath practice I
put echo awareness and certainly here at
all the Lord we meet ecological
awareness because designing and doing
practice in the in the new world has to
do with being ecologically aware but I
also mean it in terms of systems view or
ecological systems view because if you
have a systems view of your practice
then it's going to inform better inform
and better generate or engineer or
design your project so the practice is
of echo awareness and how things fit
into the system and to really bring that
down into your life skills so that that
being ecologically aware of the whole
entire system both human and non-human
as a practice and making that real right
down in terms of your life school skills
is the practice that makes
project practical so those are the three
streams that are all the lower soul is
built upon and these three are seen as
generating and self-organizing a
profound learning experience we can look
at each one of these three streams in a
different way so that for example this
stream contemplative science being the
core which generates insight into the
research I put as a stream of
understanding so the goal of this is
understanding in the skill or the
competency that it intends is clarity of
purpose so you can see how these all
work to build more clarity of purpose
and it's the stream of understanding so
what are some of the particulars in the
street clarity of purpose on deriving
meaning being able to make these are
more like core capacities being able to
derive meaning make important and
relevant distinctions discovering
patterns and looking for innovation not
to just repeat what's been done before
in the project stream here we have at
the core the community and it which
requires the embodied leadership to
manifest your project and I call that
the leading stream to leave to be like a
project manager and the capacity that
this is cultivating is adequate
participation so in order to gain
insight into your research to really
understand there's a certain level of
participation that is required enough of
a real-life project enough leadership
enough community adequate participation
in your project is the capacity that is
being cultivated in that stream and if
we look at core skills the ability to
its enactment skills the ability to take
a vision and enact it in the real world
the ability to do action inquiry and all
of these can be looked at in much more
detail and another core skill is to
inspire people to be inspirational
because you need a community to resource
your project so those would be some core
skills that are addressed through this
experiential stream of leading and the
last stream which is the practice dream
I say that that's the stream of creating
but there's something physical something
very practical and physical left in the
world so we have on life skills as the
basic fundamental orientation toward a
creative life for actually creating your
the structures of your own life's a very
practical stream
hear the echo awareness that your life
is nested inside a larger system and
systems of systems including human and
non-human systems and that that it's
cultivated through long-term process and
the capacity that Steve being developed
in the creating stream I call
sensitivity for conditions and this is
also something that is being left out in
education today that students can have a
lot of good ideas and a lot of resources
but they're not sensitive to real-life
conditions it's relatively impractical
they can't they can't they can't discern
the subtle changes in appreciation or
relevance or meaningfulness and so
sensitivities to conditions I think is a
very critical capacity for us to
cultivate in our children as the core
skills and would be being able to create
a method to understand systems to have
some design skills and to be inventive
so this is the process dreams generative
stream of all the lures self-organizing
learning experience